<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Enchiridion </title>
        <author>Epictetus</author>
        <editor role="editor" n="transl">Thomas Wentworth Higginson</editor>
        <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
        <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
          <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
          <name>William Merrill</name>
          <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
          <name>David Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
      </publicationStmt>



      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Works of Epictetus: His Discourses, in Four Books, the Enchiridion, and
              Fragments</title>
            <author>Epictetus</author>
            <respStmt>
              <name>Thomas Wentworth Higginson</name>
              <name>Gregory Crane</name>
              <resp>translator</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <imprint>
              <pubPlace>New York/Medford, MA</pubPlace>
              <publisher>Thomas Nelson and Sons/Tufts University</publisher>
              <date>1890/2020</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>

    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction method="silent" status="high">
          <!--&Perseus.OCR;-->
          <p>Perseus OCR</p>
        </correction>
      </editorialDecl>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState unit="text"/>
        <refState unit="book"/>
        <refState n="chunk" unit="chapter"/>
      </refsDecl>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState unit="text"/>
        <refState n="chunk" unit="chapter"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>

    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
        <language ident="greek">Greek</language>
        <language ident="la">Latin</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>

    <revisionDesc>
      <!--
<change><date>03-Dec-03</date>
<respStmt><name>AEM</name><resp>markup</resp></respStmt>
<item>initial markup
</item>
</change>
<change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split composite text and converted to unicode</item>
      </change>-->
      <change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
      <change when="2020-01-24" who="Gregory Crane">began revision</change>
    </revisionDesc>

  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <body>
      <head>The Enchiridion</head>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="1">
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>There are things which are within our power, and there are things which are beyond our
          power. </s>
          
          <s>Within our power are opinion, aim, desire, aversion, and, in one word, whatever
          affairs are our own. 
          </s>
          <s>     
          Beyond our power are body, property, reputation, office, and, in one
          word, whatever are not properly our own affairs.</s></p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
          <p><s>Now, the things within our power are by nature free, unrestricted, unhindered; but those
            beyond our power are weak, dependent, restricted, alien.</s></p></div>
        
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p><s>Remember, then, that if you
          attribute freedom to things by nature dependent, and take what belongs to others for your
          own, you will be hindered, you will lament, you will be disturbed, you will find fault
          both with gods and men. 
          
        </s>
          <s>But if you take for your own only that which is your own, and view
          what belongs to others just as it really is, then no one will ever compel you, no one will
          restrict you, you will find fault with no one, you will accuse no one, you will do nothing
          against your will; no one will hurt you, you will not have an enemy, nor will you suffer
          any harm. <pb n="p.2216"/></s></p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p><s>Aiming therefore at such great things, remember that you must not allow yourself any
          inclination, however slight, towards the attainment of the others; but that you must
          entirely quit some of them, and for the present postpone the rest. But if you would have
          these, and possess power and wealth likewise, you may miss the latter in seeking the
          former; and you will certainly fail of that by which alone happiness and freedom are
          procured.</s></p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"> <p><s>Seek at once, therefore, to be able to say to every unpleasing semblance, " You are but a
          semblance and by no means the real thing." And then examine it by those rules which you
          have; and first and chiefly, by this: whether it concerns the things which are within our
          own power, or those which are not; and if it concerns anything beyond our power, be
          prepared to say that it is nothing to you.</s></p>
   </div>   </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="2"> <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>Remember that desire demands the attainment of that of which you are desirous; and
          aversion demands the avoidance of that to which you are averse; that he who fails of the
          object of his desires is disappointed; and he who incurs the object of his aversion is
          wretched. </s>
          
          <s>If, then, you shun only those undesirable things which you can control, you will
          never incur anything which you shun; but if you shun sickness, or death, or poverty, you
          will run the risk of wretchedness. </s></p></div>
        
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p><s>Remove [the habit of] aversion, <pb n="p.2217"/> 
          then, from all things that are not within our power, and apply it to things undesirable,
          which are within our power. But for the present altogether restrain desire;</s>
          <s>for if you
          desire any of the things not within our own power, you must necessarily be disappointed;
          and you are not yet secure of those which are within our power, and so are legitimate
          objects of desire.  </s>
          <s>Where it is practically necessary for you to pursue or avoid anything,
          do even this with discretion, and gentleness, and moderation.</s></p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="3">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>With regard to whatever objects either delight the mind, or contribute to use, or are
          tenderly beloved, remind yourself of what nature they are, beginning with the merest
          trifles:</s>
        <s> if you have a favorite cup, that it is but a cup of which you are fond, - for
          thus, if it is broken, you can bear it;</s>
        <s> if you embrace your child, or your wife, that you
          embrace a mortal, - and thus, if either of them dies, you can bear it.</s></p>
      </div>
</div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="4">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>When you set about any action, remind yourself of what nature the action is.</s>
        <s> If you are
          going to bathe, represent to yourself the incidents usual in the bath, - some persons
          pouring out, others pushing in, others scolding, others pilfering.</s>
        <s> And thus you will more
          safely go about this action, if you say to yourself, " I will now go to bathe, and keep my
          own will <pb n="p.2218"/> in harmony with nature." And so with regard to every other
          action. </s>
        <s>For thus, if any impediment arises in bathing, you will be able to say, "It was
          not only to bathe that I desired, but to keep my will in harmony with nature; and I shall
          not keep it thus, if I am out of humor at things that happen."</s></p>
      </div>
</div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="5">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>Men are disturbed not by things, but by the views which they take of things.</s>
        <s> Thus death
          is nothing terrible, else it would have appeared so to <placeName key="tgn,2674867"
            >Socrates</placeName>. But the terror consists in our notion of death, that it is
          terrible. </s>
        <s>When, therefore, we are hindered, or disturbed, or grieved, let us never impute
          it to others, but to ourselves; that is, to our own views. </s>
        <s>It is the action of an
          uninstructed person to reproach others for his own misfortunes; of one entering upon
          instruction, to reproach himself; and of one perfectly instructed, to reproach neither
          others nor himself.</s></p>
      </div>
</div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="6">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>Be not elated at any excellence not your own. If a horse should be elated, and say, " I
          am handsome," it might be endurable.</s>
        <s> But when you are elated, and say, " I have a handsome
          horse," know that you are elated only on the merit of the horse. </s>
        <s>What then is your own?</s>
        <s>
          The use of the phenomena of existence.</s>
        <s> So that when you are in harmony with nature in this
            <pb n="p.2219"/> respect, you will be elated with some reason; </s>
        <s>for you will be elated at
          some good of your own.</s></p>
      </div>
</div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="7">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>As in a voyage, when the ship is at anchor, if you go on shore to get water, you may
          amuse yourself with picking up a shell-fish or a truffle in your way, but your thoughts
          ought to be bent towards the ship, and perpetually attentive, lest the captain should
          call, and then you must leave all these things, that you may not have to be carried on
          board the vessel, bound like a sheep;</s>
        <s> thus likewise in life, if, instead of a truffle or
          shell-fish, such a thing as a wife or a child be granted you, there is no objection;</s>
        <s> but
          if the captain calls, run to the ship, leave all these things, and never look behind. </s>
        <s>But
          if you are old, never go far from the ship, lest you should be missing when called
          for.</s></p>
      </div>
</div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="8">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>Demand not that events should happen as you wish; </s>
        <s>but wish them to happen as they do
          happen, and you will go on well.</s></p>
      </div>
</div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="9">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>Sickness is an impediment to the body, but not to the will, unless itself pleases.</s>
        <s>
          Lameness is an impediment to the leg, but not to the will; </s>
        <s>and say this to yourself with
          regard to everything that happens. </s>
        <s>For <pb n="p.2220"/> you will find it to be an
          impediment to something else, but not truly to yourself.</s></p>
      </div>
</div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="10">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>Upon every accident, remember to turn towards yourself and inquire what faculty you have
          for its use.</s>
        <s> If you encounter a handsome person, you will find continence the faculty
          needed; </s>
        <s>if pain, then fortitude; </s>
        <s>if reviling, then patience. </s>
        <s>And when thus habituated, the
          phenomena of existence will not overwhelm you.</s></p>
      </div>
</div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="11">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>Never say of anything, "I have lost it;" but, " I have restored it." </s>
        <s>Has your child died?</s>
        <s>
          It is restored. </s>
        <s>Has your wife died? </s>
        <s>She is restored. </s>
        <s>Has your estate been taken away? </s>
        <s>That
          likewise is restored. </s>
        <s>" But it was a bad man who took it." </s>
        <s>What is it to you by whose
          hands he who gave it has demanded it again? </s>
        <s>While he permits you to possess it, hold it as
          something not your own; as do travellers at an inn.</s></p>
      </div>
</div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="12">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>If you would improve, lay aside such reasonings as these:</s>
        <s> "If I neglect my affairs, I
          shall not have a maintenance;" </s>
        <s> "if I do not punish my servant, he will be good for nothing."
          </s>
        <s>For it were better to die of hunger, exempt from grief and fear, than to live in affluence
          with perturbation; </s>
        <s>and it is better that your servant should be bad than you unhappy. <pb
            n="p.2221"/></s></p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
        <p><s>Begin therefore with little things. </s>
        <s>Is a little oil spilt or a little wine stolen? </s>
        <s>Say to
          yourself, "This is the price paid for peace and tranquillity; and nothing is to be had for
          nothing." </s>
        <s>And when you call your servant, consider that it is possible he may not come at
          your call; or, if he does, that he may not do what you wish. </s>
        <s>But it is not at all
          desirable for him, and very undesirable for you, that it should be in his power to cause
          you any disturbance.</s></p>
      </div>
</div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="13">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>If you would improve, be content to be thought foolish and dull with regard to externals.
          </s>
        <s>Do not desire to be thought to know anything; and though you should appear to others to be
          somebody, distrust yourself. </s>
        <s>For be assured, it is not easy at once to keep your will in
          harmony with nature, and to secure externals; </s>
        <s>but while you are absorbed in the one, you
          must of necessity neglect the other.</s></p>
      </div>
</div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="14">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>If you wish your children and your wife and your friends to live forever, you are
          foolish;</s>
        <s> for you wish things to be in your power which are not so; and what belongs to
          others to be your own.</s>
        <s> So likewise, if you wish your servant to be without fault, you are
          foolish; </s>
        <s>for you wish vice not to be vice, but something else. </s>
        <s>But if you wish not to be
          disappointed in your desires, that is in your own power. </s>
        <s>Exercise, <pb n="p.2222"/>
          therefore, what is in your power. </s></p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p><s>A man's master is he who is able to confer or remove
          whatever that man seeks or shuns. </s>
        <s>Whoever then would be free, let him wish nothing, let
          him decline nothing, which depends on others;</s>
    <s> else he must necessarily be a slave.</s></p>
      </div>
</div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="15">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>Remember that you must behave as at a banquet.</s>
        <s> Is anything brought round to you? </s>
        <s>Put out
          your hand, and take a moderate share. </s>
        <s>Does it pass by you? Do not stop it. </s>
        <s>Is it not yet
          come? </s>
        <s>Do not yearn in desire towards it, but wait till it reaches you. </s>
        <s>So with regard to
          children, wife, office, riches;</s>
        <s> and you will some time or other be worthy to feast with
          the gods. </s>
        <s>And if you do not so much as take the things which are set before you, but are
          able even to forego them, then you will not only be worthy to feast with the gods, but to
          rule with them also. </s>
        <s>For, by thus doing, Diogenes and Heraclitus, and others like them,
          deservedly became divine, and were so recognized.</s></p>
      </div>
</div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="16">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>When you see any one weeping for grief, either that his son has gone abroad, or that he
          has suffered in his affairs, take care not to be overcome by the apparent evil; </s>
        <s>but
          discriminate, and be ready to say, "What hurts this man is not this occurrence itself,-
          for another man might not be hurt by it, - but the view he chooses to take of it." </s>
        <s>As far
          as conversation <pb n="p.2223"/> goes, however, do not disdain to accommodate yourself to
          him, and if need be, to groan with him. Take heed, however, not to groan inwardly too.</s></p>
      </div>
</div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="17">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>Remember that you are an actor in a drama of such sort as the author chooses, - </s>
        <s>if short,
          then in a short one; </s>
        <s>if long, then in a long one. </s>
        <s>If it be his pleasure that you should
          enact a poor man, see that you act it well; </s>
        <s>or a cripple, or a ruler, or a private
          citizen. </s>
        <s>For this is your business, to act well the given part; </s>
        <s>but to choose it, belongs
          to another.</s></p>
      </div>
</div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="18">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>When a raven happens to croak unluckily, be not overcome by appearances, </s>
        <s>but
          discriminate, and say, " Nothing is portended to <emph>me</emph>; but either to my paltry
          body, or property, or reputation, or children, or wife. But to <emph>me</emph> all
          portents are lucky, if I will. For whatsoever happens, it belongs to me to derive
          advantage therefrom."</s></p>
      </div>
</div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="19">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>You can be unconquerable, if you enter into no combat in which it is not in your own
          power to conquer. </s></p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p><s>When, therefore, you see any one eminent in honors or power, or in high
          esteem on any other account, take heed not to be bewildered by appearances and to
          pronounce him happy; </s>
        <s>for if the essence of <pb n="p.2224"/> good consists in things within
          our own power, there will be no room for envy or emulation. </s>
        <s>But, for your part, do not
          desire to be a general, or a senator, or a consul, but to be free; </s>
        <s>and the only way to
          this is a disregard of things which lie not within our own power.</s></p>
      </div>
</div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="20">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>Remember that it is not he who gives abuse or blows who affronts; but the view we take of
          these things as insulting. </s>
        <s>When, therefore, any one provokes you, be assured that it is
          your own opinion which provokes you. </s>
        <s>Try, therefore, in the first place, not to be
          bewildered by appearances. </s>
        <s>For if you once gain time and respite, you will more easily
          command yourself.</s></p>
      </div>
</div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="21">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>Let death and exile, and all other things which appear terrible, be daily before your
          eyes, but death chiefly; </s>
        <s>and you will never entertain any abject thought, nor too eagerly
          covet anything.</s></p>
      </div>
</div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="22">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>If you have an earnest desire towards philosophy, prepare yourself from the very first to
          have the multitude laugh and sneer, and say, "He is returned to us a philosopher all at
          once;" and "Whence this supercilious look? " </s>
        <s>Now, for your part, do not have a
          supercilious look indeed; </s>
        <s>but keep steadily to those <pb n="p.2225"/> things which appear
          best to you, as one appointed by God to this particular station. </s>
        <s>For remember that, if you
          are persistent, those very persons who at first ridiculed will afterwards admire you. </s>
        <s>But
          if you are conquered by them, you will incur a double ridicule.</s></p>
      </div>
</div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="23">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>If you ever happen to turn your attention to externals, for the pleasure of any one, be
          assured that you have ruined your scheme of life. </s>
        <s>Be contented, then, in everything, with
          being a philosopher; and if you wish to seem so likewise to any one, appear so to
          yourself, and it will suffice you.</s></p>
      </div>
</div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="24">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>Let not such considerations as these distress you: "I shall live in discredit, and be
          nobody anywhere." </s>
        <s>For if discredit be an evil, you can no more be involved in evil through
          another, than in baseness.</s>
        <s> Is it any business of yours, then, to get power, or to be
          admitted to an entertainment? </s>
        <s>By no means. </s>
        <s>How then, after all, is this discredit? </s>
        <s>And how
          is it true that you will be nobody anywhere; when you ought to be somebody in those
          things only which are within your own power, in which you may be of the greatest
          consequence? </s></p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p><s> "But my friends will be unassisted." </s>
        <s>What do you mean by unassisted? </s>
        <s>They
          will not have money from you;</s>
        <s> nor will you make them Roman citizens. </s>
        <s>Who told you, then,
          that these are <pb n="p.2226"/> among the things within our own power, and not rather the
          affairs of others? </s>
        <s>And who can give to another the things which he himself has not? </s>
        <s>"Well, but get them, then, that we too may have a share." </s></p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p><s>If I can get them with the
          preservation of my own honor and fidelity and self-respect, show me the way, and I will
          get them;</s>
        <s> but if you require me to lose my own proper good, that you may gain what is no
          good, consider how unreasonable and foolish you are. </s>
    <s>Besides, which would you rather have,
          a sum of money, or a faithful and honorable friend? </s>
    <s>Rather assist me, then, to gain this
          character, than require me to do those things by which I may lose it. </s></p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p><s>"Well, but my
country," say you, "as far as depends upon me, will be unassisted." Here, again, what
          assistance is this you mean? It will not have porticos nor baths of your providing? And
          what signifies that? Why, neither does a smith provide it with shoes, nor a shoemaker with
          arms. It is enough if every one fully performs his own proper business. And were you to
          supply it with another faithful and honorable citizen, would not he be of use to it? Yes.
          Therefore neither are you yourself useless to it. "What place, then," say you, " shall I
          hold in the state?" Whatever you can hold with the preservation of your fidelity and
          honor. But if, by desiring to be useful to that, you lose these, how can you serve your
          country, when you have become faithless and shameless? <pb n="p.2227"/></s></p>
      </div>
</div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="25">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>Is any one preferred before you at an entertainment, or in courtesies, or in confidential
          intercourse? </s>
    <s>If these things are good, you ought to rejoice that he has them; </s>
    <s>and if they
          are evil, do not be grieved that you have them not. </s>
    <s>And remember that you cannot be
          permitted to rival others in externals, without using the same means to obtain them. </s></p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p><s> For
          how can he who will not haunt the door of any man, will not attend him, will not praise
          him, have an equal share with him who does these things? </s>
        <s>You are unjust, then, and
          unreasonable, if you are unwilling to pay the price for which these things are sold, and
          would have them for nothing. </s>
        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p><s>For how much are lettuces sold?</s>
    <s> An obolus, for instance. </s>
    <s>If
          another, then, paying an obolus, takes the lettuces, and you, not paying it, go without
          them, do not imagine that he has gained any advantage over you. </s>
    <s>For as he has the
          lettuces, so you have the obolus which you did not give. </s></p>
    </div>

    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p><s>So, in the present case, </s>
        <s>you have
          not been invited to such a person's entertainment, because you have not paid him the price
          for which a supper is sold. </s>
        <s>It is sold for praise; it is sold for attendance. </s>
        <s>Give him,
          then, the value, if it be for your advantage. </s>
        <s>But if you would at the same time not pay
          the one, and yet receive the other, you are unreasonable and foolish. </s>
        <s>Have you nothing,
          then, in place of the supper? </s>
        <s>Yes, indeed you have: not <pb n="p.2228"/> to praise him
          whom you do not like to praise; not to bear the insolence of his lackeys.</s></p>
      </div>
</div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="26">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>The will of Nature may be learned from things upon which we are all agreed. </s>
        <s>As, when our
          neighbor's boy has broken a cup, or the like, we are ready at once to say, " These are
          casualties that will happen;" </s>
        <s>be assured, then, that when your own cup is likewise broken,
          you ought to be affected just as when another's cup was broken. </s>
        <s>Now apply this to greater
          things.</s>
        <s> Is the child or wife of another dead? </s>
        <s>There is no one who would not say, " This is
          an accident of mortality." </s>
        <s>But if any one's own child happens to die, it is immediately,
          "Alas ! how wretched am I! " </s>
        <s>It should be always remembered how we are affected on hearing
          the same thing concerning others.</s></p>
      </div>
</div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="27">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>As a mark <note n='1'/> is not set up for the sake of missing the aim, so neither does the nature of
          evil exist in the world.</s></p>
      </div>
</div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="28">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>If a person had delivered up your body to some passer-by, you would certainly be angry.
         </s>
        <s> And do <note anchored="true">Happiness, the effect of virtue, is the mark which God hath
            set up for us to aim at. Our missing it is no work of His; nor so properly anything
            real, as a mere negative and failure of our own. - C.</note>
          <pb n="p.2229"/> you feel no shame in delivering up your own mind to any reviler, to be
          disconcerted and confounded?</s></p>
      </div>
</div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="29">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>In every affair consider what precedes and follows, and then undertake it. </s>
        <s>Otherwise
            you will begin with spirit indeed, careless of the consequences, and when these are
            developed, you will shamefully desist.</s>
        <s> " I would conquer at the Olympic Games." </s></p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p><s>So would I, by the gods!</s>
<s>It is very cool.<note>GRC</note></s>
<s> But
            consider what precedes and follows, and then engage in the
            affair. </s>
        <s>You must conform to rules, submit to a diet, refrain from dainties; exercise
            your body, whether you choose it or not, at a stated hour, in heat and cold; you must
            drink no cold water, and sometimes no wine, -in a word, you must give yourself up to
            your trainer as to a physician. </s>
        <s>Then, in the combat, you may be thrown into a ditch,
            dislocate your arm, turn your ankle, swallow abundance of dust, sometimes receive stripes [for
            negligence], and, after all, lose the victory. </s></p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p><s> When you have reckoned up all this, if
            your inclination <pb n="p.2049"/>  still holds, set about the combat. </s>
        <s>Otherwise, take
            notice, you will behave like children who sometimes play wrestlers, sometimes
            gladiators; sometimes blow a trumpet, and sometimes act a tragedy, when they happen to
            have seen and admired these shows.</s>
        <s> Thus you too will be at one time a wrestler, at
            another a gladiator; now an orator, now a philosopher; but nothing in earnest. </s>
        <s> Like an
            ape you mimic all you see, and one thing after another is sure to please you, </s>


        <s>  For you have never entered upon anything
            considerately, nor after having surveyed and tested the whole matter; but carelessly,
            and with a half-way zeal. </s></p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p><s>Thus some, when they have seen a philosopher, and heard a man
            speaking like <placeName key="tgn,1123842">Euphrates</placeName>,<note anchored="true"
                ><placeName key="tgn,1123842">Euphrates</placeName> was a philosopher of <placeName
                key="tgn,1000140">Syria</placeName>, whose character is described, with the highest
              encomiums, by Pliny. See L. I. Ep.x.-C.</note>--though indeed who can speak like him?-
            have a mind to be philosophers too. </s>


        <s>Consider first, man, what the matter is, and what
            your own nature is able to bear. </s>


        <s>If you would be a pentathlete or a wrestler, consider your shoulders,
            your back, your thighs; </s></p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p><s>for different persons are made for different things. </s>


        <s>Do you
            think  that you can eat, drink, be
            angry, be discontented, as you are now? You must watch, you must labor, you must get the
            better of certain appetites; must quit your acquaintances, be despised by your <pb
              n="p.2050"/> servant, be laughed at by those you meet; come off worse than others in
            everything, - in honors, in offices,  before tribunals, in every small thing.  </s>


       </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7"><p> <s>Consider these things.</s>

<s> if, by parting with them, you have a mind to
            purchase serenity, freedom, and tranquillity. </s>

<s>If not, do not come hither; </s>

<s>do not, like
            children, be now a philosopher, then a publican, then an orator, and then one of
            Caesar's officers. </s>

<s>These things are not consistent. </s>

<s>You must be one man either good or
            bad. </s>

<s>You must cultivate either your own Reason or else externals; </s>

<s>apply yourself either
            to things within or without you; </s>

<s>that is, be either a philosopher, or one of the
            mob.<note>This chapter, except some very trifling differences, is the same with the fifteenth of
          the third book of the Discourses.-H; I have made a first pass at adapting Higginson's translation of Disc. 3.15 but this needs to be checked -- GRC.</note></s></p>
      </div>
</div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="30">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>Duties are universally measured by relations.</s>
        
        <s> Is a certain man your father? </s>
        
        <s>In this are
          implied, taking care of him; submitting to him in all things; patiently receiving his
          reproaches, his correction. </s>
        
        <s>But he is a bad father. </s>
        
        <s>Is your natural tie, then, to a
            <emph>good</emph> father?</s>
        
        <s> No, but to a father. </s>
        
        <s>Is a brother unjust? </s>
        
        <s>Well, preserve your
          own just relation towards him. </s>
        
        <s>Consider not what <emph>he</emph> does, but what
            <emph>you</emph> are to do, to keep your own will in a state conformable to nature. </s>
        
        <s>For
          another cannot hurt you, unless you please. </s>
        
        <s>You will then be hurt when you consent to be
          hurt. </s>
        
        <s>In this manner, therefore, if you accustom yourself to contemplate the relations of
          neighbor, citizen, commander, you can deduce from each the corresponding duties.</s></p>
      </div>
</div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="31">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>Be assured that the essence of piety towards the gods lies in this, to form right
          opinions concerning them, as existing, and as governing the universe justly and well. And
          fix yourself in this resolution, to obey them, and yield to them, and willingly follow <pb
            n="p.2230"/> them amidst all events, as being ruled by the most perfect wisdom. For thus
          you will never find fault with the gods, nor accuse them of neglecting you.  </s></p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p><s>And it is not
          possible for this to be effected in any other way than by withdrawing yourself from things
          which are not within our own power, and by making good or evil to consist only in those
          which are. </s>
        
        <s> For if you suppose any other things to be either good or evil, it is inevitable
          that, when you are disappointed of what you wish, or incur what you would avoid, you
          should reproach and blame their authors. </s></p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p><s> For every creature is naturally formed to flee
          and abhor things that appear hurtful, and that which causes them; and to pursue and admire
          those which appear beneficial, and that which causes them.</s>
    
    <s> It is impracticable, then, that
          one who supposes himself to be hurt should rejoice in the person who, as he thinks, hurts
          him; just as it is impossible to rejoice in the hurt itself.</s>
    
   </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p> <s> Hence, also, a father is
          reviled by his son, when he does not impart the things which seem to be good; </s>
    
    <s>and this
          made Polynices and Eteocles mutually enemies, that empire seemed good to both.</s>
    
    <s> On this
          account the husbandman reviles the gods; the sailor, the merchant, or those who have lost
          wife or child. </s>
    
    <s>For where our interest is, there too is piety directed.</s>
    
    <s> So that whoever is
          careful to regulate his desires and aversions as he ought is thus made careful of piety
          likewise.</s>
    
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>    <s> But it also becomes incumbent on every one to offer libations and sacrifices and
            <pb n="p.2231"/> first-fruits, according to the customs of his country, purely, and not
          heedlessly nor negligently; not avariciously, nor yet extravagantly.</s></p>
      </div>
</div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="32">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>When you have recourse to divination, remember that you know not what the event will be,
          and you come to learn it of the diviner; but of what nature it is you knew before coming;
          at least, if you are of philosophic mind. </s>
    
    <s> For if it is among the things not within our own
          power, it can by no means be either good or evil. </s></p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p><s> Do not, therefore, bring with you to the
          diviner either desire or aversion, - else you will approach him trembling, -but first
          clearly understand that every event is indifferent, and nothing to <emph>you</emph>, of
          whatever sort it may be; for it will be in your power to make a right use of it, and this
          no one can hinder.</s>
        
        <s> Then come with confidence to the gods as your counsellors; </s>
        
        <s>and
          afterwards, when any counsel is given you, remember what counsellors you have assumed, and
          whose advice you will neglect, if you disobey. </s></p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p><s>Come to divination, as <placeName
            key="tgn,2674867">Socrates</placeName> prescribed, in cases of which the whole
          consideration relates to the event, and in which no opportunities are afforded by reason,
          or any other art, to discover the matter in view. </s>
    
    <s>When, therefore, it is our duty to share
          the danger of a friend or of our country, we ought not to consult the oracle as to whether
          we shall share it with them or not. </s>
    
    <s>For though the diviner should forewarn <pb n="p.2232"
          /> you that the auspices are unfavorable, this means no more than that either death or
          mutilation or exile is portended. </s>
    
    <s>But we have reason within us; and it directs us, even
          with these hazards, to stand by our friend and our country. </s>
    
    <s>Attend, therefore, to the
          greater diviner, the Pythian God, who once cast out of the temple him who neglected to
          save his friend.<note anchored="true">This refers to an anecdote given in full by
            Simplicius, in his commentary on this passage, of a man assaulted and killed, on his way
            to consult the oracle, while his companion, deserting him, took refuge in the temple,
            till cast out by the Deity.- H.</note></s></p>
      </div>
</div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="33">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>Begin by prescribing to yourself some character and demeanor, such as you may preserve
          both alone and in company.</s></p>
        </div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p><s>Be mostly silent; or speak merely what is needful, and in few words. We may, however,
          enter sparingly into discourse sometimes, when occasion calls for it; but let it not run
          on any of the common subjects, as gladiators, or horse-races, or athletic champions, or
          food, or drink, -the vulgar topics of conversation;</s>
    
    <s> and especially not on men, so as
          either to blame, or praise, or make comparisons. </s></p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p><s>If you are able, then, by your own
          conversation, bring over that of your company to proper subjects; </s>
    
    <s> but if you happen to
          find yourself among strangers, be silent.</s></p>
       </div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"> <p><s>Let not your laughter be loud, frequent, or abundant. <pb n="p.2233"/></s></p>
       </div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"> <p><s>Avoid taking oaths, if possible, altogether; at any rate, so far as you are able.</s></p>
        <p><s>Avoid public and vulgar entertainments; </s></p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p><s>  but if ever an occasion calls you to them, keep
          your attention upon the stretch, that you may not imperceptibly slide into vulgarity.</s>
    
    <s> For
          be assured that if a person be ever so pure himself, yet, if his companion be corrupted,
          he who converses with him will be corrupted likewise.</s></p>
     </div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7">   <p><s>Provide things relating to the body no farther than absolute need requires; as meat,
          drink, clothing, house, retinue. </s>
    <s> But cut off everything that looks towards show and
          luxury.</s></p>
        <p><s>Before marriage, guard yourself with all your ability from unlawful intercourse with
          women; </s></p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8"><p><s>yet be not uncharitable or severe to those who are led into this, nor frequently
          boast that you yourself do otherwise.</s></p>
       </div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9"> <p><s>If any one tells you that such a person speaks ill of you, do not make excuses about what
          is said of you, but answer: "He was ignorant of my other faults, else he would not have
          mentioned these alone."</s></p>
      </div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10">  <p><s>It is not necessary for you to appear often at public spectacles;</s>
    <s> but if ever there is a
          proper occasion for you to be there, do not appear more solicitous for any other than for
          yourself; </s>
    <s>that is, wish things to be only just as they are, and only the best man to win;
         </s>
    <s> for thus nothing will go against you. </s>
    <s>But abstain entirely from acclamations and derision
          and violent emotions. </s>
    <s> And when you come away, do not discourse a great <pb n="p.2234"/>
          deal on what has passed, and what contributes nothing to your own amendment. </s>
    <s> For it would
          appear by such discourse that you were dazzled by the show.</s></p>
      </div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11">  <p><s>Be not prompt or ready to attend private recitations; but if you do attend, preserve your
          gravity and dignity, and yet avoid making yourself disagreeable.</s></p>
        </div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12"><p><s>When you are going to confer with any one, and especially with one who seems your
          superior, represent to yourself how <placeName key="tgn,2674867">Socrates</placeName> or
            <placeName key="tgn,2786859">Zeno</placeName> would behave in such a case, and you will
          not be at a loss to meet properly whatever may occur.</s></p>
       </div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13"> <p><s>When you are going before any one in power, fancy to yourself that you may not find him
          at home, that you may be shut out, that the doors may not be opened to you, that he may
          not notice you. </s>
    <s>If, with all this, it be your duty to go, bear what happens, and never say
          to yourself, "It was not worth so much." </s>
    <s>For this is vulgar, and like a man bewildered by
          externals.</s></p>
       </div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14"> <p><s>In society, avoid a frequent and excessive mention of your own actions and dangers.</s>
    <s> For
          however agreeable it may be to yourself to allude to the risks you have run, it is not
          equally agreeable to others to hear your adventures. </s>
 </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15"><p>   <s> Avoid likewise an endeavor to excite
          laughter..</s>
    <s> For this may readily slide you into vulgarity, and, besides, may be apt to lower
          you in the esteem of your acquaintance..</s>
   ></p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16"><p> <s> Approaches to <pb n="p.2235"/> indecent discourse
          are likewise dangerous.</s>
    <s> Therefore when anything of this sort happens, use the first fit
          opportunity to rebuke him who makes advances that way;</s>
    <s> or, at least, by silence and
          blushing and a serious look, show yourself to be displeased by such talk.</s></p>
      </div>
</div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="34">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>If you are dazzled by the semblance of any promised pleasure, guard yourself against
          being bewildered by it; </s>
        <s> but let the affair wait your leisure, and procure yourself some
          delay.</s>
        <s>  Then bring to your mind both points of time, -that in which you shall enjoy the
          pleasure, and that in which you will repent and reproach yourself, after you have enjoyed
          it, -</s>
        <s>  and set before you, in opposition to these, how you will rejoice and applaud
          yourself, if you abstain.</s>
        <s>  And even though it should appear to you a seasonable
          gratification, take heed that its enticements and allurements and seductions may not
          subdue you; </s>
        <s> but set in opposition to this, how much better it is to be conscious of having
          gained so great a victory.</s></p>
      </div>
</div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="35">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>When you do anything from a clear judgment that it ought to be done, never shrink from
          being seen to do it, even though the world should misunderstand it;</s>
        <s>  for if you are not
          acting rightly, shun the action itself;</s>
        <s>  if you are, why fear those who wrongly censure
          you? <pb n="p.2236"/></s></p>
      </div>
</div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="36">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>As the proposition, <emph>either it is day, or it is night</emph>, has much force in a
          disjunctive argument, but none at all in a conjunctive one; so, at a feast, to choose the
          largest share is very suitable to the bodily appetite, but utterly inconsistent with the
          social spirit of the entertainment. </s>
        <s> Remember, then, when you eat with another, not only
          the value to the body of those things which are set before you, but also the value of
          proper courtesy towards your host.</s></p>
      </div>
</div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="37">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>If you have assumed any character beyond your strength, you have both demeaned yourself
          ill in that, and quitted one which you might have supported.</s></p>
      </div>
</div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="38">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>As in walking you take care not to tread upon a nail, or turn your foot, so likewise take
          care not to hurt the ruling faculty of your mind.</s>
        <s>  And if we were to guard against this in
          every action, we should enter upon action more safely.</s></p>
      </div>
</div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="39">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>The body is to every one the proper measure of its possessions, as the foot is of the
          shoe.</s>
        <s> If, therefore, you stop at this, you will keep the measure;</s>
        <s> but if you move beyond
          it, you must necessarily be carried forward, as down a precipice; </s>
        <s> as in the case of a <pb
            n="p.2237"/> shoe, if you go beyond its fitness to the foot, it comes first to be
          gilded, then purple, and then studded with jewels.</s>
        <s> For to that which once exceeds the fit
          measure there is no bound.</s></p>
      </div>
</div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="40">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>Women from fourteen years old are flattered by men with the title of mistresses.
       </s>
        <s>   Therefore, perceiving that they are regarded only as qualified to give men pleasure, they
          begin to adorn themselves, and in that to place all their hopes.</s>
        <s> It is worth while,
          therefore, to try that they may perceive themselves honored only so far as they appear
          beautiful in their demeanor, and modestly virtuous.</s></p>
      </div>
</div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="41">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>It is a mark of want of intellect, to spend much time in things relating to the body; as
          to be immoderate in exercises, in eating and drinking, and in the discharge of other
          animal functions.</s>
        <s> These things should be done incidentally and our main strength be
          applied to our reason.</s></p>
      </div>
</div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="42">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>When any person does ill by you, or speaks ill of you, remember that he acts or speaks
          from an impression that it is right for him to do so. </s>
        <s> Now, it is not possible that he
          should follow what appears right to you, but only what appears so to himself. Therefore,
          if he judges from false appearances, he is the <pb n="p.2238"/> person hurt; since he too
          is the person deceived. </s>
        <s> For if any one takes a true proposition to be false, the
          proposition is not hurt, but only the man is deceived. </s>
        <s> Setting out, then, from these
          principles, you will meekly bear with a person who reviles you;</s>
        <s> for you will say upon
          every occasion, "It seemed so to him."</s></p>
      </div>
</div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="43">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>Everything has two handles: one by which it may be borne, another by which it cannot.</s>
        <s> If
          your brother acts unjustly, do not lay hold on the affair by the handle of his injustice,
         </s>
        <s> for by that it cannot be borne; </s>
        <s> but rather by the opposite, that he is your brother, that
          he was brought up with you; and thus you will lay hold on it as it is to be borne.</s></p>
      </div>
</div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="44">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>These reasonings have no logical connection: "I am richer than you; therefore I am your
          superior." </s>
        <s>"I am more eloquent than you; therefore I am your superior." </s>
        <s> The true logical
          connection is rather this: "I am richer than you; therefore my possessions must exceed
          yours." </s>
        <s>" I am more eloquent than you; therefore my style must surpass yours." </s>
        <s>But you,
          after all, consist neither in property nor in style.</s></p>
      </div>
</div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="45">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>Does any one bathe hastily?</s>
        <s> Do not say that he does it ill, but hastily. </s>
        <s>Does any one
          drink much <pb n="p.2239"/> wine? </s>
        <s>Do not say that he does ill, but that he drinks a great
          deal.</s>
        <s> For unless you perfectly understand his motives, how should you know if he acts ill?
          </s>
        <s>Thus you will not risk yielding to any appearances but such as you fully comprehend.</s></p>
      </div>
</div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="46">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>Never proclaim yourself a philosopher; nor make much talk among the ignorant about your
          principles, but show them by actions.</s>
        <s> Thus, at an entertainment, do not discourse how
          people ought to eat; but eat as you ought.</s>
        <s> For remember that thus <placeName
            key="tgn,2674867">Socrates</placeName> also universally avoided all ostentation. And
          when persons came to him, and desired to be introduced by him to philosophers, he took
          them and introduced them;</s></p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p><s>  so well did he bear being overlooked. </s>
        <s>So if ever there should be
          among the ignorant any discussion of principles, be for the most part silent.</s>
        <s> For there is
          great danger in hastily throwing out what is undigested.</s>
        <s> And if any one tells you that you
          know nothing, and you are not nettled at it, then you may be sure that you have really
          entered on your work. </s>
        <s>For sheep do not hastily throw up the grass, to show the shepherds
          how much they have eaten; but, inwardly digesting their food, they produce it outwardly in
          wool and milk. </s>
        <s>Thus, therefore, do you not make an exhibition before the ignorant of your
          principles; but of the actions to which their digestion gives rise. <pb n="p.2240"/></s></p>
      </div>
</div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="47">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>When you have learned to nourish your body frugally, do not pique yourself upon it; nor,
          if you drink water, be saying upon every occasion, " I drink water." </s>
        <s>But first consider
          how much more frugal are the poor than we, and how much more patient of hardship.<note>I don't see this in the Greek -- GRC: 1/30/2020</note> If at
          any time you would inure yourself by exercise to labor and privation,</s>
        <s> for your own sake
          and not for the public,</s>
        <s> do not attempt great feats; </s>
        <s>but when you are violently thirsty,
          just rinse your mouth with water, and tell nobody.</s></p>
      </div>
</div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="48">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>The condition and characteristic of a vulgar person</s>
        <s> is that he never looks for either
          help or harm from himself, but only from externals. </s>
        <s>The condition and characteristic of a
          philosopher </s>
        <s>is that he looks to himself for all help or harm.</s></p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p><s> The marks of a proficient
          are that he censures no one, praises no one, blames no one, accuses no one;</s>
        <s> says nothing
          concerning himself as being anybody, or knowing anything. </s>
        <s>When he is in any instance
          hindered or restrained, he accuses himself; </s>
        <s>and if he is praised, he smiles to himself at
          the person who praises him;</s>
        <s> and if he is censured, he makes no defence. </s>
        <s>But he goes about
          with the caution of a convalescent, careful of interference with anything that is doing
          well, but not yet quite secure.</s></p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p><s> He restrains desire; he transfers his aversion to those
          things only which thwart the <pb n="p.2241"/> proper use of our own will;</s>
        <s> he employs his
          energies moderately in all directions;</s>
        <s> if he appears stupid or ignorant, he does not care;
         </s>
        <s> and, in a word, he keeps watch over himself as over an enemy and one in ambush.</s></p>
      </div>
</div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="49">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>When any one shows himself vain, on being able to understand and interpret the works of
          Chrysippus, say to yourself: "Unless Chrysippus had written obscurely, this person would
          have had nothing to be vain of." </s>
        <s> But what do I desire? </s>
        <s>To understand Nature, and follow
          her. </s>
        <s>I ask, then, who interprets her;</s>
        <s> and hearing that Chrysippus does, I have recourse to
          him. </s>
        <s>I do not understand his writings.</s>
        <s> I seek, therefore, one to interpret
            <emph>them</emph>. </s>
        <s>So far there is nothing to value myself upon.</s>
        <s> And when I find an
          interpreter, what remains is to make use of his instructions.</s>
        <s> This alone is the valuable
          thing. </s>
        <s>But if I admire merely the interpretation, what do I become more than a grammarian,
          instead of a philosopher,</s>
        <s> except, indeed, that instead of Homer I interpret Chrysippus?
          </s>
        <s>When any one, therefore, desires me to read Chrysippus to him, I rather blush, when I
          cannot exhibit actions that are harmonious and consonant with his discourse.</s></p>
      </div>
</div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="50">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>Whatever rules you have adopted, abide by them as laws, and as if you would be impious to
          transgress <pb n="p.2242"/> them; </s>
        <s>and do not regard what any one says of you, for this,</s>
        <s>
          after all, is no concern of yours.</s></p>
      </div>
</div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="51">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>How long, then, will you delay to demand of yourself the noblest improvements, and in no
          instance to transgress the judgments of reason? </s>
        <s>You have received the philosophic
          principles with which you ought to be conversant; and you have been conversant with them.
          </s>
        <s>For what other master, then, do you wait as an excuse for this delay in self-reformation?
          </s>
        <s>You are no longer a boy, but a grown man. </s>
        <s>If, therefore, you will be negligent and
          slothful, and always add procrastination to procrastination, purpose to purpose, and fix
          day after day in which you will attend to yourself, you will insensibly continue to
          accomplish nothing, and, living and dying, remain of vulgar mind.</s></p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p><s> This instant, then,
          think yourself worthy of living as a man grown up and a proficient.</s>
        <s> Let whatever appears
          to be the best, be to you an inviolable law. </s>
        <s>And if any instance of pain or pleasure,
          glory or disgrace, be set before you, remember that now is the combat, now the Olympiad
          comes on, nor can it be put off; and that by one failure and defeat honor may be lost - or
          won. Thus <placeName key="tgn,2674867">Socrates</placeName> became perfect, improving
          himself by everything, following reason alone. And though you are not yet a <placeName
            key="tgn,2674867">Socrates</placeName>, you ought, however, to live as one seeking to be
          a <placeName key="tgn,2674867">Socrates</placeName>. <pb n="p.2243"/></s></p>
      </div>
</div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="52">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>The first and most necessary topic in philosophy is the practical application of
          principles, as, <emph>We ought not to lie</emph>;</s>
        <s> the second is that of demonstrations,
          as, <emph>Why it is that we ought not to lie</emph>;</s>
        <s> the third, that which gives strength
          and logical connection to the other two, as, <emph>Why this is a demonstration</emph>.</s>
        <s> For
          what is demonstration? What is a consequence; what a contradiction; what truth; what
          falsehood? </s></p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p><s>The third point is then necessary on account of the second; and the second on
          account of the first.</s>
        <s>  But the most necessary, and that whereon we ought to rest, is the
          first.</s>
        <s> But we do just the contrary. </s>
        <s>For we spend all our time on the third point, and
          employ all our diligence about that,</s>
        <s> and entirely neglect the first. </s>
        <s>Therefore, at the
          same time that we lie, we are very ready to show how it is demonstrated that lying is
          wrong.</s></p>
      </div>
</div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="53">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
        <p><s>Upon all occasions we ought to have these maxims ready at hand: </s>- <cit>
            <quote><lb/><s>Conduct me, Zeus, and thou, O Destiny,
              <lb/>Wherever your decrees have fixed my lot.</s>
              <lb/><s>I follow cheerfully;</s><s> and, did I not,
              <lb/>Wicked and wretched, I must follow still.</s></quote>
            <bibl>Cleanthes, in Diogenes Laertius, quoted also by Seneca, Epistle 107.- H.</bibl>
          </cit>
          <pb n="p.2244"/>
          <cit>
            <quote><lb/><s>Whoe'er yields properly to Fate is deemed
              <lb/>Wise among men, and knows the laws of Heaven.</s></quote>
            <bibl>Euripides, Fragments.</bibl>
          </cit> - H. And this third: - <cit>
            <quote><s>O Crito, if it thus pleases the gods, thus let it be.</s></quote>
            <bibl n="Plat. Crito 54e">Plato, Crito,17</bibl>
          </cit>-H. <cit>
            <quote><s>Anytus and Melitus may kill me indeed; but hurt me they cannot.</s></quote>
            <bibl n="Plat. Apol. 30c">Apology, 18.</bibl>
          </cit> -H. <pb n="p.2245"/></p>
      </div>
</div>
    </body>
  </text>

</TEI>
